A Guide to the William Fielding Baugh Papers, 1861-1905
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Fielding Baugh Papers, 1861-1905
The Library of Virginia
45019
.45 cu. ft. and 1 box
William Fielding Baugh
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Francis W. Baugh of Carson, Virginia.
Alternative Form Available
Letters Home: Letters of Lt. Wm. F. Baugh Co. G 61st. Va. Infantry 1861-1865 transcribed by Roy N. Cain.
Biographical Information
William Fielding Baugh was born 3 May 1839 in Sussex County, Virginia, to John Mason Baugh and Amanda Caroline Rose Baugh (b. ca. 1816). He attended Richmond College and became a school teacher. Baugh enlisted in the "Confederate Defenders" which became Company G, 61st Virginia Infantry. He served with the regiment throughout the war and saw service at Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, and the siege of Petersburg (including the battle of the Crater). After the war, he became a farmer in Dinwiddie County, Virginia, and served as a magistrate for the county. Baugh married Mary Frances "Pinkie" Coker (b. 1842) 16 July 1862 and they had 10 children, 7 of whom reached adulthood. Baugh died 19 May 1910 and was buried on his farm in Dinwiddie County.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1861-1905, of William Fielding Baugh of Company G, 61st Virginia Infantry, consisting of letters mainly to his wife Mary Frances "Pinkie" Coker Baugh (b. 1842) and to his mother Amanda Caroline Rose Baugh (b. ca. 1816) detailing Baugh's life as an officer in the 61st Virginia including descriptions of the battles of Fredericksburg, Chancellorsville, Gettysburg, Bristoe Station, and the Crater. Baugh records camp news, discusses family matters, and notes efforts to get leaves of absence. He comments on clothing, food, and supplies. Collection include some letters written by family members to Baugh. Most letters are published in Letters Home: Letters of Lt. Wm. F. Baugh Co. G 61ST Va. Infantry 1861-1865, also titled Letters Home: Presenting the Surviving Correspondence of Lt. W. F. Baugh CSA Co. G 61st. Virginia Infantry ANV, transcribed by Roy N. Cain (5th printing). The following letters are not in the published volume: Amanda C. Baugh to William F. Baugh, 25 March 1861; Amanda C. Baugh to William F. Baugh, 15 January 1862; William F. Baugh to Mary Frances "Pinkie" Coker, [28 March 1862?]; William F. Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 19 December 1864; Virginius N. Baugh to William F. Baugh, 12 April 1864; H. K. Reid to William F. Baugh, 3 October 1903.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
The original of one of the letters dated 4 December 1905 is located at the Eleanor S. Brockenbrough Library, the Museum of the Confederacy, Richmond, Virginia.
Contents List
- Letter from Amanda C. Baugh to William Fielding Baugh, 25 March 1861 (letter is not included in Letters Home). (Folder 1)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 13 May 1861 (includes copy). (Folder 1)
- Letter from Amanda C. Baugh to William Fielding Baugh, 15 January 1862 (letter is not included in Letters Home). (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 19 February 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to unknown recipient, 25 February 1862. (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 28 February 1862. (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 14 March 1862. (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Coker, 23 March 1862. (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Coker, [28 March 1862?] (Letter is not included in Letters Home). (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to [Mary Frances Pinkie Coker], 29 March 1862. (Folder 2)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 1 April 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 3)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 10 April 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 3)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to [Mary Frances Pinkie Coker], 11 April 1862. (Folder 3)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh and Leonora Nolie Baugh, 20 April 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 3)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh with note from Amanda C. Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Coker, 25 April [1862] (no date on the note). (Folder 3)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to [Mary Frances Pinkie Coker], 1 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 12 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Coker, 13 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter from William F. Niemeyer to William Fielding Baugh, 22 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 23 May 1862. (Folder 4)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 29 May 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 4)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to [Mary Frances Pinkie Coker], 9 June 1862. (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to unknown recipient, 15 June 1862 (incomplete?) [Letter 22 in Letters Home]. (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, [June-July 1862?] [Letter 20 in Letters Home]. (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to [Mary Frances Pinkie Coker], [June-July 1862?] [Letter 21 in Letters Home]. (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh (nee Coker), 28 [July?] 1862 (faded). (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 29 July 1862. (Folder 5)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 3 August 1862. (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 4 August 1862 (includes copy). (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, [?] August 1862 (faded). (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 16 August [1862]. (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 29 August 1862. (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 September 1862 (faded). (Folder 6)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 6 November 1862 (envelope). (Folder 7)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 13 November 1862. (Folder 7)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 19 November [1862]. (Folder 7)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 & 25 November 1862. (Folder 7)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 1 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 2 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 4 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 9 & 18 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 15 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 December 1862. (Folder 8)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 3 January 1863. (Folder 9)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 4 January 1863 (includes copy). (Folder 9)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 26 January 1863 (envelope). (Folder 9)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 31 January 1863. (Folder 9)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 5 February 1863 (includes copy) (faded). (Folder 10)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 6 February 1863 (faded). (Folder 10)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 12 & 16 February 1863 [Second section of letter listed as letter 48, no date-1st four pages missing in Letters Home]. (Folder 10)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 24 February 1863. (Folder 10)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 2 March 1863. (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 4 March 1863 (includes copy). (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 10 March 1863. (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 17 March 1863 (envelope). (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 March 1863. (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 30 March 1863. (Folder 11)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 4 April 1863 (faded). (Folder 12)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 5 April 1863. (Folder 12)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 11 April 1863 (includes copy) (faded). (Folder 12)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh [and note from Amanda C. Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh], 27 April 1863 [and after 1 May 1863]. (Folder 12)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 5 May 1863. (Folder 13)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 7 May 1863 [Second section of letter listed as letter 54, [April 1863?] in Letters Home]. (Folder 13)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 13 May 1863 (incomplete). (Folder 13)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 May 1863. (Folder 13)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 29 May 1863. (Folder 13)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 12 June 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 16 June 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 22 June 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 7 July 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 16 July 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 31 July 1863. (Folder 14)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh [and Amanda C. Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh written on envelope], 1 August 1863 [and August 1863]. (Folder 15)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 8 August 1863. (Folder 15)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 15 August 1863. (Folder 15)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 18 August 1863. (Folder 15)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 23 August 1863. (Folder 15)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 15 September 1863. (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 28 September 1863 (envelope). (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 4 October 1863. (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 16 October 1863. (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 20 October 1863. (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 25 October 1863. (Folder 16)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 1 November 1863 (faded). (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 2 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 4 November 1863 (includes copy). (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 4 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 10 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 13 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 18 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 24 November 1863. (Folder 17)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 4 December 1863. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 8 December 1863. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 16 December 1863 (envelope). (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 19 December 1863 (Letter not included in Letters Home). (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 19 December 1863. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 23 December 1863. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, [no date] [Transcriber of Letters Home places this letter as late December 1863, but it is possible April 1863--see William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh 4 April 1863]. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 26 December 1863. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 27 December 1863 (faded). (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 31 December 1863 and 1 January 1864. (Folder 18)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 6 January 1864. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 8 January 1864. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 11 January 1864. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh [and note made by William Fielding Baugh], 19 January 1864 [and note 11 March 1864]. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 23 January 1864 (envelope). (Folder 19)
- Letter from Lulie Jenkins to William Fielding Baugh, 24 January 1864 [Letter 118 in Letters Home]. (Folder 19)
- Request for leave of absence by William Fielding Baugh, 26 January 1864, and endorsements. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Amanda C. Baugh, 30 January 1864 (envelope). (Folder 19)
- Request for leave of absence by William Fielding Baugh, 21 February 1864, and endorsements. (Folder 19)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 7 April 1864. (Folder 20)
- Letter from Virginius N. Baugh to William Fielding Baugh, 12 April 1864 (Letter is not included in Letters Home]. (Folder 20)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 13 April 1864. (Folder 20)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 4 May 1864. (Folder 20)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 28 May 1864. (Folder 20)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 9 November 1864. (Folder 21)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 15 December 1864. (Folder 21)
- Request for leave of absence by William Fielding Baugh, 20 December 1864, and endorsements. (Folder 21)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 12 January 1865. (Folder 22)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 3 February 1865. (Folder 22)
- Letter from Amanda C. Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, no date. (Folder 22)
- Letter from H. K. Reid to William Fielding Baugh, 3 October 1903 (Letter not included in Letters Home). (Folder 23)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to William H. Stewart, 4 December 1905 (incomplete?). (Folder 23)
- Letter from William Fielding Baugh to William H. Stewart, 4 December 1905 (Photocopy--original of this letter located at Eleanor S. Brockenbrough Library, Museum of the Confederacy, Richmond, Virginia). (Folder 23)
- Envelopes, some containing notes from Amanda C. Baugh to Mary Frances Pinkie Baugh, 1862-1865. (Folder 24)
- Illegible letter, unknown date. (Folder 24)
- Illegible letter, unknown date. (Folder 24)